SOFTWARE ENGINEER/EDI SPECIALIST

Career Overview

Extensive software development and consulting experience including analysis, implementation and mentoring. I have worked on projects closely aligned with any or all of the business units including logistics, shipping and distribution, accounting, sales, inventory management, sales reporting, procurement and more. Proficient in interpreting, designing and programming reliable software solutions and also effective in a consulting or business analyst role.

Qualifications

- IBM I-series Developer on WDSE platform using CL, RPGLE
- Experienced with several EDI translator and mapping products including TIE Commerce eVision Suite, GXS Trusted Link EDI and STX
- Deep knowledge of ANSI-X12, EDIFAC, TRADACOMS EDI Standards
- Effective at communicating with representatives at all levels of an organization from end-user to CIO/CEO.
- Manage2000 ERP/MRP System experience
- Strong analytical skills and significant experience resolving software support issues, including discovery and resolution of software defects.
- Microsoft Office 2010 (Access, Excel, PowerPoint, Word)

Technical Skills

Skills	Experience	Total Years	Last Used
IBM iSeries/AS400 CL/RPGLE programming		8	7/24/15
WDSE for I-series		8	7/26/15
AS2		17	7/26/15
IBM DB2/SQL		8	7/26/15
XML		17	7/24/15
Unix Unibasic/Uniquery programming		17	1/12/15
PHP		10	3/1/07
Work Experience			

Software Engineer/EDI Specialist

October 2007 to July 2015 Patterson Companies, Inc - City, STATE

- Provide software programming solutions on the IBM I-series platform for new business applications using RPGLE, CL and SQL
- Software engineering and customization specializing in EDI business transaction development for sales order processing, procure to pay, inventory receipt, inventory catalog and level transactions.
- Developed and implemented a process to import UPS small package freight invoices as EDI 210 transactions. Previously this process required several hours of manual download, document conversion and error checking weekly. The new process now takes 5 minutes once weekly to import invoices into back end AP system.
- Provided solution to convert daily 867 sales reporting transactions from a series of manual steps to a single control program with scheduling. The result saves 45 minutes of daily user time daily.
- Created CL and ILE programs and EDI mappings for new transaction sets including ANSI X12 856(Advance Ship Notice), 855(PO acknowledgment), 832(Item catalog) and 210(Freight Invoice).
- Program software enhancements on IBM platform to meet specific vendor requirements for 867(Product Transfer and Resale Report), 852(Product Activity) and 210(Freight Invoice) and other related transactions, Patterson Companies is a large volume distributor and product replenishment efficiency and responding to vendor requests are a key component to their success.
- Received special recognition for bringing a new major vendor on board as an EDI partner on a very short timeline which gave Patterson Companies a major strategic advantage in negotiating a new vendor agreement.
- Currently involved with the development of SAP/EDI/AS400 integration solutions for Patterson Companies large multi company software migration. This effort includes customization of CL and RPGLE programs to work concurrently with existing back end system and the new SAP modules.
- Led effort to install AS2 communications to replace ftp for greater reliability and tracking and move major trading partners to new platform. This allowed for direct connections with trading partners and provided significant savings in monthly VAN charges.
- Managed major EDI trading partner on boarding initiative for the medical division. This effort involved the addition of 150+ vendors in total as EDI partners who had previously been emailing or faxing critical documents.
- Continually provide ongoing EDI support, including program customization and defect resolution, mapping services, and new trading partner implementation for Patterson Dental, Veterinary and Medical companies.
- Received special recognition for bringing a new major vendor on board as an EDI partner on a very short timeline which gave Patterson Companies a major strategic advantage in negotiating a new vendor agreement.

Software Engineer/EDI Analyst

February 2004 to October 2007 Epicor Software Corporation - City, STATE

 Software development, customization, implementation and training for ERP manufacturing clients with focus on sales to cash, inventory management and distribution using EDI transaction sets.

- Managed projects from beginning to end including requirements gathering, creating EDI transactions mappings, program customization and process enhancement, implementation and training.
- Mapping and implementation services included ANSI X12 transaction sets 210,211,850,810,855,830,832,852, 856,870,940 and 945.
- Trained internal and external clients to manage their EDI installation including how to build and schedule workflows, troubleshoot error
 conditions, update mappings, and add new partners and transactions. This would include training on the TIE Commerce eVision translator
 and Epicor software products.
- Exceeded billable hour target goals each year.

Software Engineer/EDI Specialist

August 1997 to February 2004 ROI Systems, Inc - City, STATE

- Software development, customization, implementation and training for ERP manufacturing clients.
- Manage-2000 product customization team member.
- Development projects included software version upgrades and client installations, enhancements to the standard software product per specific customer requirements and add custom functionality.
- Programmed software solutions ranging from reports and label print programs to sales order pricing and inventory reservations with special emphasis on EDI related functions and processes.
- A specific example is an enhancement to the Ship Manifest function to automate the UCC128 label assignment by shipping container to feed the outbound EDI ASN transaction. This improved process was then sold to additional software customers.
- Provided on-site and in-house training and EDI support for users including software clients, programmers, helpline technicians and consultants.
- One of two EDI specialists who serviced the entire ROI Systems customer base. In this role I would provide consulting, training, business analysis, process flow and technical support for EDI.Often these services were performed at client site.
- Managed EDI implementation projects for new and existing ERP clients from initial contact through deployment.
- Specific tasks included building EDI transaction mappings, set-up of production workflows and communications protocols for document delivery (AS2) and training on related Manage2000 and TIE Commerce eVision software.

Education and Training

B.A: Computer Information Systems, 2005 Metropolitan State University - City, State

Computer Information Systems

A.A: 1994 Inver Hills Community College

Member Phi Betta Kappa National Honor Society

CPIM Training APICS

Skills

AS400, business analysis, AS2,sftp,ftps,communications protocols, consulting, IBM I-series team lead, logistics, Access, Excel, Microsoft Office, Microsoft Outlook, Software development, Software engineering, SQL, strategic, technical support, Translator, troubleshoot, UCC, Unix, Unibasic, Uniquery, iSeries, PHP